<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The way to excel. Meditations, awakened by the death of the reverend Mr. Joshua Moodey; with some short character of the eminent person: who slept in Jesus, 4d. 5 m. 1697.  In the sixty fifth year of his age / by Cotton Mather.</title>
            <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 53KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09520</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">69648828</idno>
  <idno type="VID">185005</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240871639</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing M1167</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC W19638</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">69648828</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09520)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 185005)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2883:28)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The way to excel. Meditations, awakened by the death of the reverend Mr. Joshua Moodey; with some short character of the eminent person: who slept in Jesus, 4d. 5 m. 1697.  In the sixty fifth year of his age / by Cotton Mather.</title>
                  <author>Mather, Cotton, 1663-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>32 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by B. Green, and J. Allen,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Boston, in N. E. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1697.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Massachusetts Historical Society Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Moodey, Joshua, 1633?-1697 --  Death and burial.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Funeral sermons --  Massachusetts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Sermons, American --  Massachusetts --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-09 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="modern_bookplate">
            <pb facs="tcp:185005:1"/>
            <p> Massachusetts Historical Society</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:185005:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:185005:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:185005:2"/>
            <p>
               <hi>The Way to Excel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>MEDITATIONS, Awakened by the DEATH of the Reverend Mr. Joshua Moodey; With some Short Character of that Eminent Person: Who</hi> Slept in <hi>Jesus,</hi> 4d. 5. m. 1697.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>In the Sixty fifth year of his Age.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>By <hi>Cotton Mather.</hi>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Josh. XXIV.</hi> 22, 23, 29.</bibl>
               <p>JOSHUA said unto the People,—ye have Chosen you the Lord, to Serve Him.</p>
               <p>Now therefore Incline your Heart unto the Lord.</p>
               <p>And it came to pass, after these things, that <hi>Ioshua,</hi> the Servant of the Lord, Dyed.</p>
            </q>
            <p>BOSTON, <hi>in</hi> N. E.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Printed by</hi> B. Green, <hi>and</hi> J. Allen.</p>
            <p>1697.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:185005:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:185005:3"/>
            <opener>
               <salute>Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>TELL me not, that the Peoples being Taken with <hi>Publicola's</hi> Funeral Oration in Praise of the Dead <hi>Brutus,</hi> or the Decree of the <hi>Roman Senate,</hi> That it should be Lawful to make a Funeral Oration on such as deserved well of the Common wealth, made <hi>Polydore Virgil</hi> say, <hi>Hinc mortuos Laudandi mos fluxit, quem nos hodie Servamus.</hi> The Book of <hi>Lamentations,</hi> on the Death of <hi>Josiah,</hi> is of an Elder Date; The Roll of <hi>Lamentations,</hi> on the Death of <hi>Jonathan,</hi> is of yet an Elder; And cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, to be Imitated among the faithful People of God. Tell me not, that some Eminent <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformists</hi> have therefore Scrupled, the Preaching of any <hi>Funeral Sermons:</hi> that in some <hi>Reformed Churches,</hi> the Practice of them is wholly omitted; that in the <hi>Primitive Churches,</hi> they were not practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced until the <hi>Apostasy</hi> began; and that there have been <hi>Decrees of Councils</hi> against them. I readily grant, That the Custome of <hi>Praising the Dead,</hi> ha's been Scandalously Abused; but I cannot grant, That the Abuse is best Corrected, by taking away all <hi>Publick Meditations,</hi> on the <hi>Funerals</hi> of Those, in whose <hi>Deaths</hi> God from Heaven speaks Great Things unto the <hi>Living.</hi> We do but wisely Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fil our Ministry, by <hi>Watching,</hi> to suit the <hi>Words</hi> of
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:185005:4"/> God, unto those <hi>Works</hi> of His, which occur to our Notice, when <hi>Men of Note</hi> are taken away. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, According to the Laudable usage in the Churches of <hi>New England,</hi> the <hi>Meditations</hi> which have been <hi>Awakened,</hi> by the falling <hi>Asleep</hi> of an Eminent Person, who was, <hi>A Memorable Servant of those Churches!</hi> I am out of measure Astonish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, when I read in an Author as old, and as great as <hi>Austin,</hi> the Wonderful Effects, which the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Reliques</hi> of the Martyr <hi>Stephen</hi> had upon those who repaired thereunto, for the cure of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies. The best sort of <hi>Reliques,</hi> are those which we have here preserved, &amp; proposed; &amp; it will be no <hi>Superstition,</hi> to hope, that a cure of Spiritual Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ladies too generally prevailing, may be promoted, by Repairing unto them. And, I do not more question the Opinion of a very Learned man, concerning the <hi>Angels,</hi> whom we find mention'd in the Scriptures as doing very <hi>Humane</hi> Actions, <hi>Veros Homines fuisse, qui a Spiritu Messiae, et a Spiriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus Angelicis agebantur; et movebantur ad ea Agenda, quae ipsi non intelligebant, phantasia Eorum obsessa, et a Cogitationibus consuetis abducta: Qui Homines, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotio peracto▪ ad quod fuerant a Deo adhibiti, discusso veterno, et cessante Ecstasi, ad Consueta munera reversi sunt, immemores eorum, quae Impulsore Spiritu Divino, aut Angelico, egerant:</hi> Than I do believe, That in our <hi>Actions,</hi> there is an Imitation of the Holy <hi>Angels</hi> to be endeavoured, by which a man, may become another <hi>Stephen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:185005:4"/>
            <head>The way to Excel.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Acts VI.</hi> 15.</bibl>
               <q>—Looking Stedfastly on him, they saw his Face, as it had been the Face of an ANGEL.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>SInce the <hi>Oracles</hi> of Heaven, have (with a most significant Admonition!) allow'd a well served Church, to call its <hi>Pastor,</hi> by the Name of its <hi>Angel,</hi> we may now say, <hi>The Angel of the Church of</hi> Portsmouth, <hi>has newly taken wing!</hi> Yea, not the Least of the <hi>Angelical Chariots and Horsemen of</hi> New England, have de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from us, in the <hi>Withdraw</hi> of One, after whom that Bereaved Church, is crying, <hi>My Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, My Father!</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To praeserve the <hi>Idea,</hi> and <hi>Memory,</hi> of his <hi>Face,</hi> as far as the Infirmities of this <hi>Mortal State</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted any Approaches to the <hi>Angelical</hi> Chara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cter in it, is that whereto not only <hi>Nature</hi> does Invite us, but also <hi>Scripture</hi> does oblige us: 'Twill be but a compliance with that Edict of Heaven, <hi>Remember them who have spoken to you, the Word of God; whose Faith follow, considering the End of their Conversation.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:185005:5"/>
            <p>'Tis well known, That among the chief Works of the Most High, Created by the Son of God, at the First Beginning of Time, there were His <hi>Good</hi> ANGELS: <hi>Angels,</hi> which are Spiritual and Rational Substances, Created by the Lord, for His own Immediate Service and Honour. None Deny, None Dispute, the Existence of those <hi>Good Angels,</hi> but men that are under a more than ordinary Possession of <hi>Evil</hi> Ones.</p>
            <p>Our Lord Jesus Christ, has given it, as a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>scription of that <hi>Future State,</hi> wherein He will make us Happy for ever, Math. 22. 30. <hi>They are as the Angels of God in Heaven.</hi> And if we Hope, to be <hi>Happy</hi> in that <hi>Future State,</hi> we must endeavour to Anticipate it, by being very <hi>Holy</hi> in our <hi>Present State.</hi> But the way for us, to be very <hi>Holy,</hi> is to Resemble, and Imitate, the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels of God in Heaven,</hi> while we are on Earth, as far as we are able. Every <hi>Holy man</hi> does a <hi>Little</hi> of This; and <hi>how much</hi> of it, was done by that <hi>Holy man,</hi> who is now gone to Live, and Praise, and see CHRIST, among the <hi>Angels</hi> for ever, may be proposed with some Advantage unto the <hi>Exhortation,</hi> wherein I have a <hi>few Things to Preach unto the People.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But my <hi>Exhortation</hi> must be introduced, with a Report of that <hi>Glory,</hi> which the Martyr <hi>Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phen,</hi> while he was yet on Earth, attain'd unto.</p>
            <p>There being occasion to choose <hi>Deacons</hi> in the Primitive Church, that so they who were to give themselves continually unto the <hi>Ministry of</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:185005:5"/>
               <hi>the Word,</hi> might be Released, by the faithful Cares of those <hi>Deacons,</hi> from Secular Encumbran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; <hi>One</hi> of them was the Blessed <hi>Stephen;</hi> who being the First that arriv'd unto the <hi>Crown of Martyrdome</hi> for our Lord Jesus Christ, in the New-Testament, had in the Name of <hi>Stephen,</hi> which signifies, <hi>A Crown,</hi> a notable Specification, of the <hi>Event</hi> and <hi>Reward,</hi> which will attend all our <hi>Sufferings</hi> for the Lord.</p>
            <p>It was then an Age of many <hi>Miracles</hi> wrought by the <hi>Spirit</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ; and such a <hi>measure</hi> of that <hi>Spirit,</hi> possessed this Excellent man, that by the <hi>Impulse</hi> of that <hi>Spirit,</hi> He could, with all Assurance, perceive when the <hi>Spirit</hi> was going to work <hi>Miracles,</hi> and apply himself to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>company the <hi>Miracles</hi> of the <hi>Spirit,</hi> by some wonderful <hi>Actions</hi> of his own. This Illustrious Worker of <hi>Miracles,</hi> was Accused before the <hi>Council</hi> at <hi>Jerusalem,</hi> for saying, That it was the Design of <hi>Jesus,</hi> to destroy the <hi>Temple,</hi> and the <hi>City,</hi> and alter the <hi>Rites,</hi> which <hi>Moses</hi> had, from God, commanded unto <hi>Israel.</hi> When he appear'd before the <hi>Council</hi> to answer this Accusation, 'tis here said, <hi>They saw his Face, as it had been the Face of an Angel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Concerning the <hi>Face of an Angel,</hi> we have a Remarkable Account, in what we read about one of the <hi>Angels,</hi> in Mat. 28. 3. His <hi>Countenance was like Lightning.</hi> And we read concerning a Great man, who had got the <hi>Face of an Angel,</hi> by being much with the <hi>Angels,</hi> in Exod 34. 10. <hi>Behold,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:185005:6"/>
               <hi>the skin of his Face shone.</hi> If we carry the passage now before us, unto the Highest sense, which it would lay claim unto, we are to suppose, That such a <hi>Splendor</hi> was discernible upon the <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>Stephen:</hi> And surely, if they who discerned it, had not had the <hi>Heart of a Devil</hi> in them, they durst not have gone on, to Abuse a <hi>man,</hi> that Appeared before them, with the <hi>Face of an Angel.</hi> Alas, the more of an <hi>Angel</hi> there is in any <hi>man,</hi> the more <hi>Stones</hi> will the <hi>Devil</hi> procure to be thrown at such a <hi>Man!</hi> But, behold, the <hi>Agreeableness</hi> of the matter; <hi>Stephen</hi> was persecuted for vilifying of <hi>Moses;</hi> and, behold, at this very Time, he is vindicated with a <hi>Shine</hi> upon his <hi>Face,</hi> like that once upon the <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>Moses.</hi> The Things here spoken by <hi>Stephen,</hi> were those very Things, which the <hi>Angel Gabriel,</hi> had formerly spoken unto the <hi>Prophet Daniel;</hi> and behold, the Aspect of an <hi>Angel</hi> adorns him, in his Discourse.</p>
            <p>We may from hence, take Leave to Observe, <hi>That a</hi> Saint on Earth, <hi>may arrive to those Attain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, that shall make him Look like an</hi> Angel of Heaven.</p>
            <p>There are <hi>Angelical Excellencies,</hi> a Degree whereof, poor <hi>man,</hi> sorry <hi>man,</hi> sinful <hi>man,</hi> even while such, may very much attain unto.</p>
            <p>But now, this CASE calls for our Attention; <hi>What are those Excellencies, that would make a Saint, Look like an</hi> ANGEL?</p>
            <p>And the General Answer hereunto is, The <hi>Excellencies of Holiness,</hi> For,</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:185005:6"/>
            <p> First, The <hi>Angels</hi> of God, have many <hi>Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencies,</hi> the Imitation whereof cannot by men in this Life, be Reasonably proposed. The <hi>Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Majesty,</hi> as a <hi>Mortal Eye</hi> would not be able steadily to <hi>Behold</hi> it, much less, in this <hi>Mortal State,</hi> may we <hi>Affect</hi> it. A man may not wish to <hi>Shine</hi> like <hi>Stephen,</hi> in this World, and have a <hi>Face,</hi> that may dazzle the Spectators. Or, what would it avail, if a man could make a Glare on his <hi>Face,</hi> by smearing it with some of the <hi>Noctilu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ca's</hi> invented by the <hi>Modern Chymistry?</hi> A <hi>Devil</hi> has before now, pretended unto such a <hi>Face.</hi> 'Tis not the <hi>Face,</hi> but the <hi>Grace,</hi> of an <hi>Angel,</hi> which is here to be Aspired after. It were a Foolish, and a Faulty Thing, for any man, to be ambitious, of wearing in this World, such a Figure, as that in Dan. 10. 6. <hi>His Body like the Beryl, and his Face as the Appearance of Lightning, and his Eyes as Lamps of Fire. Immortality</hi> it self, is one of the <hi>Angelical Excellencies.</hi> But, while we are among <hi>Mortals</hi> here, we must submit unto the Laws of <hi>Mortality,</hi> and be willing to <hi>Dy,</hi> When, and How, the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign God shall order it. There are also, those Flights of <hi>Wisdom,</hi> and those Heights of <hi>Power</hi> among the <hi>Angelical Excellencies;</hi> wherein, 'tis not for us, to Dream of being <hi>Like</hi> them, until we are become, <hi>The Children of the Resurrection▪</hi> It was the Ruine of our <hi>First Parents,</hi> to imagine, in Gen. 3. 5. They <hi>might be as Elohim!</hi> No, this cannot be, until our Lord Jesus Christ, has by a <hi>New Birth</hi> brought us into that <hi>World to come,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:185005:7"/> where, the <hi>Wise Converters of many to Righteousness,</hi> will be those, who shall <hi>Shine as the Brightness of the Firmament, and as the Stars for ever and ever!</hi> Our Lord Jesus Christ, will make <hi>us</hi> the <hi>Angels</hi> of the <hi>New World.</hi> Indeed the <hi>Angels</hi> now turn and move all the <hi>Wheels</hi> of the <hi>Kingdoms</hi> of <hi>this World,</hi> but <hi>we</hi> are they that shall <hi>Receive the Kingdom that cannot be moved.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But, Secondly, The <hi>Excellencies of Holiness,</hi> [For, the <hi>Saints,</hi> are the <hi>Excellent!]</hi> These are They, wherein the Imitation of the <hi>Angels</hi> by <hi>men,</hi> may be very far proceeded in. The <hi>Angels</hi> of God, are styled, in Mat. 25. 31. <hi>The Holy Angels;</hi> and in Dan. 4. 17. <hi>The Holy Ones.</hi> 'Tis not as they are <hi>Mighty Angels,</hi> but as they are <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> that we must propound our coming to Look like unto them. These <hi>Holy Angels,</hi> never did, and never will Sin against their God; but are conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually Serving of Him; <hi>They Serve Him Day and Night in His Temple!</hi> And it may be, the <hi>Bright Garments,</hi> wherein these <hi>Angels of Light,</hi> have ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared, may be an Emblem of their <hi>Holiness</hi> and their <hi>Purity.</hi> Now it hath been the <hi>Will of God in our Lord Jesus Christ concerning us,</hi> that there should be set before us, the Greatest Exemples of <hi>Holiness</hi> for our Imitation. And hence, as we have the Greater <hi>Exemple</hi> of our Lord JESUS CHRIST Himself given unto us, to Direct and Excite and Promote our <hi>Holiness,</hi> with a Charge, <hi>To be Holy, as He that hath called us is Holy;</hi> So, we have also the <hi>Exemple</hi> of the <hi>Holy Angels</hi> given unto us, That
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:185005:7"/> we may strive as far as may be, to be Like unto them in their <hi>Holiness.</hi> Hence when the Psamist of old saw the <hi>Angels</hi> praising of God, he cryed out, <hi>O my Soul, do Thou so too!</hi> Yea, some Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters Judge, That when the <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>Stephen</hi> Look'd like an <hi>Angel,</hi> it was no more than what you and I may <hi>thro' Christ who strengthens us,</hi> reach unto. <hi>q d.</hi> The <hi>Consolations</hi> of the <hi>Holy Spirit</hi> of God, so filled him, that he discovered not the least <hi>Consternations</hi> in his <hi>Face:</hi> His <hi>Face</hi> was as Joyful, and Serene, as if he had stood free from all the <hi>Sorrows</hi> of this World, among the <hi>Angels</hi> of God.</p>
            <p>I remember the Apostle Enjoins the <hi>Woman</hi> in the Church to have a covering on her Head, in Token of Subjection to her <hi>Husband; Because of the Angels.</hi> [2 Cor. 11. 10.] Why, if you turn to the Beginning of the sixth Chapter of <hi>Isaiah,</hi> you'l find the <hi>Angels</hi> before their Superiour, the Lord Jesus Christ, in the <hi>Temple</hi> assuming a <hi>Cover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> out of the Reverence which they pay unto Him. Hence then, says the Apostle, it becomes <hi>Women</hi> to take <hi>Example</hi> by the <hi>Angels;</hi> let them consider, how the <hi>Angels</hi> behave themselves in the Presence of the <hi>Son</hi> of God, who is the Grand Representative of the <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of God; and let them in their <hi>Habit</hi> show some Analogy to the <hi>Habit</hi> of the <hi>Angels:</hi> betokening their Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection to the <hi>man,</hi> who is under the Lord Jesus Christ, the <hi>Image</hi> and <hi>Glory</hi> of God, while <hi>They</hi> the <hi>Women,</hi> are so of the <hi>man.</hi> But I only touch
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:185005:8"/> on this gloss, by the by. What I insist on, is, That the <hi>Angelical Example</hi> is to be imitated.</p>
            <p>Indeed, we shall, as long as we Live in this World, come far short of the <hi>Original,</hi> when we go to Write after the <hi>Angelical Example.</hi> In this <hi>Present Evil World,</hi> we cannot approach near to the <hi>Holiness</hi> of the <hi>Good Angels:</hi> Much of Sin, and Fault, &amp; Folly, will unavoidably cleave unto us: That <hi>Leprosy</hi> will never wholly out of the <hi>Walls,</hi> until the <hi>Clay-house</hi> be utterly demolished: There will be as much Distance between the <hi>Blessed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> and <hi>Us,</hi> as between <hi>Giants</hi> and <hi>Children,</hi> as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Stars</hi> and <hi>Gloworms,</hi> as between the <hi>Cedars</hi> of <hi>Lebanon,</hi> and the <hi>Hysop</hi> that <hi>Grows out of the Wall;</hi> Thus it will be, until we come at length to dwell [And, <hi>Oh! Why do we no more Long for it!]</hi> with the <hi>Innumerable Company of Angels,</hi> in another World.</p>
            <p>However, to Attempt the Imitation, is the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy way to be <hi>Excellent.</hi> Particularly in the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suing Instances.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>I.</hi> If a man could have his <hi>Eye</hi> upon the <hi>Face of God</hi> continually, would not that procure the <hi>Face of an Angel</hi> for him? It would make a man Look like an <hi>Angel,</hi> if he were Looking unto God, in the Lord Jesus Christ continually. Of the <hi>Angels</hi> there is that Account given, in Mat. 18. 10. <hi>In the Heavens, they do always behold the Face of my Father which is in the Heavens.</hi> The <hi>Angels</hi> do converse with GOD continually. And, why may not we press after a converse with GOD, a
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:185005:8"/> little Emulating the <hi>Angelical?</hi> To be <hi>Heavenly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minded,</hi> by having the <hi>God of Heaven</hi> almost al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in our minds, and by being <hi>in the Fear of God all the Day Long; This</hi> were to be as the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> are! Oh! That we were thus, <hi>Filled with all the Fulness of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First, We may have a continual <hi>Apprehension</hi> of GOD in our minds. In every <hi>Place,</hi> we may Apprehend GOD Wherever we are, we may Subscribe to that Article of the Ancient Faith, in Psal. 139. 7. Lord, <hi>Whither shall I flee from thy Presence?</hi> What if we should never be from un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Awe of such a Thought as that, <hi>The Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipresent God observes all my wayes!</hi> And we may Apprehend GOD, in every <hi>Thing.</hi> We need not stay at any <hi>Second Causes;</hi> but we may with a <hi>Spiritualized Soul,</hi> Soar up to some Notice of <hi>God</hi> in all. Upon all the Works of <hi>Creation</hi> we may say, <hi>The Finger of God is here!</hi> And we may make the Positions of the <hi>Pauline</hi> Philosophy, in Acts 17. 24, 28. <hi>God made the World, and all Things therein; In Him we Live and Move and have our Being.</hi> Upon all the Works of <hi>Providence,</hi> we may say, <hi>This comes from that God, whose Kingdome Ruleth over all.</hi> And we may make the Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions once taught by our Lord, no doubt alluding to the <hi>Two Birds,</hi> whereof one was to be <hi>killed,</hi> the other to be <hi>Let Loose into the Open Field,</hi> at the cleansing of the <hi>Leper,</hi> in Mat. 10. 29. <hi>Two Spar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rows, one of them shall not fall on the Ground without our Father.</hi> To be Led unto some Notice of
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:185005:9"/> GOD continually, This, O This, it is <hi>Angelical.</hi> 'Tis <hi>Godliness.</hi> What is <hi>Holiness,</hi> but <hi>Godliness?</hi> This were a little of the <hi>Angelical Holiness.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Our continual <hi>Apprehension</hi> of GOD, may bring a continual <hi>Dedication</hi> to GOD, upon all that we <hi>Have,</hi> and all that we <hi>Do.</hi> If we <hi>Glance</hi> at <hi>Inferiour Ends,</hi> yet we may not <hi>Stop</hi> there: All our <hi>Ends</hi> are to be Swallowed up in GOD. We should not, with any patience consent unto it, that any but GOD, should have our <hi>Strength,</hi> our <hi>Time,</hi> our <hi>All.</hi> Whatever <hi>Possessions</hi> are bestow'd upon us, we may put them under that Considera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which the <hi>House</hi> of <hi>David</hi> had, in Psal▪ 30. <hi>Tit. Dedicated Things.</hi> All our <hi>Possessions,</hi> all the Powers of our <hi>Spirits,</hi> all the Members of our <hi>Bodies,</hi> our <hi>Estates,</hi> our <hi>Credit,</hi> our Desireable <hi>Friends;</hi> we may contrive with our selve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <hi>What Acknowledg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments may GOD have out of these Things:</hi> And Improve them no farther, than as <hi>Instruments,</hi> whereby GOD may be <hi>Acknowledged.</hi> Yea, and our daily <hi>Actions;</hi> may we not be driving a <hi>Trade</hi> for GOD in all? As 'tis said, in 1 Cor. 10. 31. <hi>Whatever ye do, do all to the Glory of God:</hi> So, our <hi>Eating,</hi> our <hi>Drinking,</hi> our <hi>Sleeping,</hi> what is it for? We may distinctly say, <hi>I do This, that I may be supported in the Service of God.</hi> Thus, our <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours,</hi> our <hi>Travels,</hi> our <hi>Visits,</hi> and our Exercises of <hi>Religion,</hi> we may thus Ennoble them, <hi>I do This, I will do it carefully and cheerfully, because God hath Commanded my doing of it.</hi> A <hi>Dedication</hi> to GOD, is the proper meaning of <hi>Holiness:</hi> And very <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelical</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:185005:9"/> would be our <hi>Holiness,</hi> if we could be fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent, and constant in such Acts of <hi>Dedication.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly; Our continual <hi>Apprehension</hi> of GOD, may produce our continual <hi>Satisfaction</hi> in GOD, under all His <hi>Dispensations.</hi> Whatever <hi>Enjoyments</hi> are by God conferred upon us, where lies the <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lish,</hi> where the <hi>Sweetness</hi> of them? Truly, we may come to Relish our <hi>Enjoyments,</hi> only <hi>so far</hi> as we have something of GOD in them. It was requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in Psal. 37 4. <hi>Delight thy self in the Lord.</hi> Yea, And what if we should have no <hi>Delight,</hi> but the <hi>Lord?</hi> Let us ponder with our selves, over our <hi>Enjoyments; In these Enjoyments I See God, and by these Enjoyments I Serve God!</hi> And now, Let all our <hi>Delight</hi> in, and all our Value and Fondness, for our <hi>Enjoyments,</hi> be <hi>Only,</hi> or <hi>Mainly,</hi> upon such a <hi>Divine Score</hi> as <hi>This.</hi> As far as any of our <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments</hi> Lead us unto GOD, so far let us Relish it, Affect it, Embrace it, and Rejoyce in it; <hi>O Tast, and Feed upon God in all;</hi> and Ask for Nothing, no, not for <hi>Life</hi> it self, any further than as it may help us, in our <hi>Seeing,</hi> and our <hi>Serving,</hi> of our GOD. And then, whatever <hi>Afflictions,</hi> do lay Fetters upon us, Let us not only Remember, that we are concerned with GOD therein, but let our concernment with GOD procure a very profound <hi>Submission</hi> in our Souls. Be able to say, with him, in Psal. 39. 9. <hi>I opened not my mouth, because Thou didst it.</hi> In all our <hi>Afflictions,</hi> Let us Remark the <hi>Justice</hi> of that GOD, before whom, <hi>Why should a Living man Complain for the Punishment of his Sin?</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:185005:10"/> the <hi>Wisdom</hi> of that GOD, <hi>whose Judgments are Right;</hi> the <hi>Goodness</hi> of that GOD, who <hi>Punishes us less than our Iniquities do deserve.</hi> Let us behave our selves, as having to Do with none but GOD, in our <hi>Afflictions:</hi> And let our <hi>Afflictions</hi> make us more conformable unto GOD; which Conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty being Effected, Let us then say, <hi>'Tis Good for me that I have been Afflicted.</hi> Sirs, what were this, but a pitch of <hi>Holiness,</hi> almost <hi>Angelical!</hi> Oh! Mount up as with the <hi>Wings of Eagles,</hi> of <hi>Angels;</hi> be not a sorry, puiny, Mechanick sort of <hi>Christians</hi> any longer; but <hi>Reach Forth</hi> unto these things, that are thus before you!</p>
            <p>But, in fine, 'Tis our Lord JESUS CHRIST, who is, <hi>The Face of God. That</hi> is His <hi>Name,</hi> fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently in the Old Testament; and in this <hi>Hint,</hi> I have given you a <hi>Golden Key</hi> to come at the sense of many passages in the Sacred Pages, about, <hi>The Face of God,</hi> and, <hi>The Light of that Face:</hi> 'Twas the <hi>Messiah.</hi> Tis then our Lord JESUS CHRIST, who is to be the more <hi>Immediate Object</hi> of our <hi>Apprehensions,</hi> when we would become <hi>Angolical;</hi> 'Tis God in our Lord JESUS CHRIST: When<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever we entertain any Thing of GOD in our minds, it should be with a CHRIST, and thro' a CHRIST. Those who do all they can, to Forge a CHRISTIANITY, without a CHRIST, are so far from Like <hi>Angels</hi> of the Lord, that they are <hi>Traitors</hi> to the King of Heaven!</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>II.</hi> We may render our selves <hi>Angelical,</hi> by our Endeavours of a <hi>present,</hi> and <hi>a pleasant</hi> and an
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:185005:10"/>
               <hi>Universal Obedience,</hi> unto the Lord JESUS CHRIST, the <hi>Lord of Angels.</hi> Who's are the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels,</hi> but the <hi>Angels of the Lord?</hi> And, [as in 1 Kin. 18. 12. and Act. 8. 39.] <hi>The Spirits of the Lord.</hi> Our Lord JESUS CHRIST is the <hi>Lord General</hi> of all the <hi>Angels;</hi> He is the <hi>Lord of Hosts;</hi> and all those <hi>Hosts</hi> of Heaven are under His Command; We read in Psal. 103. 20, 21. <hi>They do His Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, Hearkening unto the Voice of His Word: They are His Ministers which do His Pleasure.</hi> The very Highest <hi>Angel</hi> in Heaven desires and studies to be a <hi>Servant</hi> of the Lord JESUS CHRIST: The Great God, would soon strike him down from Heaven, with Hot Thunder-bolts, if he did not so. Even <hi>Michael,</hi> the <hi>Archangel,</hi> ha's Receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed that Charge from God, concerning our Lord-Redeemer, <hi>Do thou Worship Him! Gabriel</hi> himself, must give this Account of himself, <hi>I stand in the presence of the Lord Jesus Christ;</hi> namely, As a <hi>Servant</hi> standing in the <hi>Presence</hi> of his Master.</p>
            <p>Come then; Let every one of us, become the <hi>Servants</hi> of our Lord JESUS CHRIST. By con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting to the Methods of <hi>Grace</hi> in the <hi>New Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant,</hi> Let us yield our selves unto our Lord JESUS CHRIST, as unto our LORD; and say, with him in Psal. 119. 38. <hi>Lord, I am thy Servant, De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted unto thy Fear.</hi> Let us Reckon it the Highest <hi>Pleasure</hi> unto our selves, to be alwayes <hi>Pleasing</hi> of our Lord Jesus Christ: Let us Esteem it the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est <hi>Honour</hi> unto our selves, to be alwayes <hi>Honouring</hi> of Him. To be, <hi>A Man of God,</hi> is to be like an
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:185005:11"/>
               <hi>Angel,</hi> An <hi>Angel</hi> was called, in Judg. 13. 8. <hi>The Man of God.</hi> We are <hi>Men of God,</hi> when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the <hi>Devoted Servants</hi> of our Lord JESUS CHRIST. Sirs, The Bright <hi>Angels</hi> of Heaven, Invite us, to become their <hi>Fellow Servants,</hi> by giving our selves up unto the work of <hi>Witnessing</hi> to the <hi>Truths</hi> and <hi>Wayes,</hi> of their Heavenly Lord. When we have Solemnly Consecrated our selves unto this Work, Then, whatever <hi>Commands</hi> our Lord JESUS CHRIST layes upon us, Let us Readily, Joyfully, Universally yield <hi>Obedience</hi> thereunto. Be upon the <hi>Wing,</hi> as the <hi>Angels</hi> are, to do every thing, that our Lord Jesus Christ would have to be done. Delay none, Despise none, Refuse none, of the <hi>Commandments,</hi> which our Lord Jesus Christ shall give unto us; but say, as in 1 Joh. 5. 3. <hi>His Commandments are not Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vous.</hi> And whatever we shall <hi>know</hi> to be <hi>Accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> unto our Lord Jesus Christ, Let us Imme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diately <hi>Do,</hi> what we <hi>know:</hi> Let this be <hi>Argument</hi> Enough unto us, for any thing, though <hi>Flesh and Blood</hi> [Body and Soul] be never so much against it: <hi>My Lord JESUS CHRIST would have me to Do this Thing!</hi> Thus our <hi>Labour</hi> should be accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to our <hi>Prayer,</hi> That <hi>the Will of God may be done on Earth, as it is in Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>III.</hi> To be ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y <hi>Serviceable</hi> is to be <hi>Angelical:</hi> To <hi>Do Good,</hi> is the Disposition of a <hi>Good Angel.</hi> Those men, whose perpetual Business, tis, <hi>To Go about for the Doing of Good,</hi> as, they are like the Lord JESUS CHRIST, [Act 10. 38.] So they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:185005:11"/> are like the <hi>Angels,</hi> that wait upon our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sus Christ. The <hi>Angels</hi> are alwayes Employ'd in some Service, for our Lord Jesus Christ, and for those that belong unto Him. 'Tis said, in Heb. 1. 14. <hi>Are they not all Ministring Spirits?</hi> Oh! Let it, in like sort, be our Ambition, to <hi>Minister</hi> some way or other, for the <hi>Good</hi> of them, that are to be the <hi>Heirs of Salvation;</hi> and let us be much and oft, in studying with our selves, <hi>What Good may I do, with those Talents, where with my Lord Jesus Christ ha's betrusted me?</hi> How many <hi>Good Offices,</hi> does the <hi>Bible</hi> Report, as done by the <hi>Angels</hi> of God, for the <hi>People</hi> of God? And, how many such <hi>Good Offices</hi> are still done, for the <hi>People</hi> of God, by the <hi>Angels</hi> of God, which <hi>Encamp as an Host about them that Fear Him?</hi> Christians, If we are advised of any <hi>Opportunity</hi> to <hi>Do Good,</hi> Let us be as Ready to do it, as the <hi>Angel</hi> that came down to the <hi>Pool</hi> of <hi>Bethesda,</hi> was to help the Misera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles assembled there. Yea, though they should be never so Poor, never so Small, never so <hi>Mean People,</hi> that we may <hi>Do Good</hi> unto, Let us be ready to Do it, with all our Hearts. The First Appari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of an <hi>Angel,</hi> that we Read in the Scripture, was to Relieve a <hi>Poor Maid,</hi> in Trouble of Spirit. The Martyr <hi>Bradford,</hi> That man had the <hi>Face</hi> of an <hi>Angel,</hi> concerning whom it was Noted, <hi>He was alwayes, either with Purse, or Tongue, or Pen, do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Good.</hi> Whatever <hi>Company</hi> we fall into, tis easy for us, ordinarily to Think, <hi>What Good may I do in this Company before I Leave it?</hi> That man
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:185005:12"/>
               <hi>Speaks with the Tongue of Angels,</hi> who will never dismiss his <hi>Company,</hi> without some Conscientious Essay, to <hi>Speak</hi> what shall be <hi>Profitable</hi> unto them. And, <hi>Inventions</hi> to <hi>Do Good,</hi> and be <hi>Benefactors</hi> to all that are about us, the more <hi>Upright</hi> we are, the more we shall <hi>seek out many such Inventions.</hi> There is an <hi>Angelical Air</hi> upon them!</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>IV. Near Approaches</hi> to God, in <hi>Devotions</hi> and <hi>Communions,</hi> full of <hi>Intimacy</hi> with Him, will give a man, if not the <hi>Face,</hi> yet the <hi>Heart</hi> of an <hi>Angel.</hi> When was it, that the <hi>Face</hi> of <hi>Moses,</hi> had an <hi>Ange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical,</hi> and an Extraordinary <hi>Lustre</hi> upon it? It was, when he had been <hi>with God, in the Mount.</hi> We read, in Exod. 34. 29. <hi>When Moses came down from Mount Sinai, with the Two Tables of Testimony, the Skin of his Face shone.</hi> They that are very much with God, in those Exercises, wherein the <hi>Power of Godliness,</hi> does mainly consist, will con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract a <hi>Lustre</hi> therefrom, and be somewhat like the <hi>Angels,</hi> made <hi>Partakers of the Divine Nature.</hi> To be often in <hi>Secret Prayers,</hi> and <hi>Secret Praises,</hi> with Raised Strains of <hi>Heavenly Zeal</hi> before the Lord, <hi>This</hi> is to be as it were, of the <hi>Angelical Fraternity!</hi> Yea, 'Tis a <hi>Golden</hi> Passage of <hi>Chrysos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tome, That the very Angels themselves, cannot but Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour the man, whom they see Familiarly and Frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Admitted unto the Audience, and as it were Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>course with the Divine Majesty.</hi> Truly, whether the <hi>Angels</hi> may <hi>Reverence</hi> these <hi>men</hi> or no, these <hi>men</hi> do <hi>Resemble</hi> the <hi>Angels.</hi> It becomes more
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:185005:12"/> Notably thus, when men do often set apart <hi>whole Dayes,</hi> for their <hi>Prayers,</hi> and their <hi>Praises,</hi> and are <hi>With God in the Mount,</hi> for <hi>whole Dayes</hi> together. Great Things did the <hi>Angels</hi> do for <hi>Moses,</hi> Great Things for <hi>Elias,</hi> who often spent <hi>whole Dayes</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone with the Lord; And what said an <hi>Angel</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Daniel,</hi> when he had been spending <hi>whole Days</hi> at such a rate, <hi>Thou art a man of Desires, and an Angel thinks not much to fly down from Heaven unto thy Conversation!</hi> Such <hi>Dayes,</hi> do leave an <hi>Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Savour</hi> upon the <hi>Souls</hi> of men; they Leave our <hi>Souls,</hi> for many Dayes afterward, under such a Gracious, and Generous, and Serious, &amp; Watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, and Useful <hi>Biass,</hi> as has the <hi>Face</hi> of an <hi>Angel</hi> thereupon. And therefore, the <hi>Lords Dayes;</hi> Let us keep <hi>them</hi> with a peculiar Sollicitude, a singular Elevation, of <hi>Sanctity.</hi> It was the privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of <hi>John,</hi> in Rev. 1. 10. To be <hi>in the Spirit on the Lords Day.</hi> Syrs, If we are so, we shall be <hi>with the Angels on the Lords Day;</hi> And if <hi>with</hi> them, then <hi>like</hi> them. To be wholly under the <hi>Confinement,</hi> [I mistook the word, I should say, <hi>Liberty!]</hi> of <hi>Religious Applications,</hi> throughout our whole <hi>Christian Sabbath,</hi> Let us not count it, as a Ceremonious person once call'd it, <hi>A being on the Rack a whole Day together. Angels</hi> have strang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly visited and comforted some on the <hi>Rack;</hi> but never such as complain'd, that a strict <hi>Lords Day</hi> put 'em on a <hi>Rack.</hi> During the whole Day, Let our <hi>Thoughts</hi> be full of <hi>God,</hi> and <hi>Christ,</hi> and <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven;</hi> During the whole Day, Let our <hi>words</hi> be
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:185005:13"/>
               <hi>Few,</hi> and <hi>Fitt,</hi> and <hi>Savoury,</hi> and such as may <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nister Grace unto the Hearers;</hi> During the whole Day, Let our <hi>Earthly Defilements</hi> be Banished from us; Let our Hearts, be every Hour Sallying forth with Numberless <hi>Ejaculations</hi> to the Lord. Such <hi>Lords Dayes,</hi> will <hi>Ripen</hi> men into <hi>Angels</hi> at the Last! But on the <hi>Lords-Day,</hi> there sometimes does Recur, a most special and signal opportunity to <hi>Draw near unto God;</hi> namely, <hi>The Lords Supper;</hi> an Ordinance of the <hi>Nearest Fellowship</hi> with Heaven; an Ordinance, wherein a CHRIST Suffering for us, is, by the Symbols of <hi>Bread</hi> and <hi>Wine</hi> so tendred unto the Faithful, that in their Obeving His Appointment thereof, they do with Ineffable Advantage partake of Him. Well then, Let our <hi>Preparations</hi> for this Great Ordinance, be with as much of Solemnity, as if we were to <hi>Dy</hi> our selves, at the Time, when we do <hi>Annun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciate</hi> here the <hi>Death of our Lord.</hi> Let us <hi>Examine</hi> our selves, &amp; <hi>Supplicate</hi> our God, before we come to the <hi>Table</hi> of the Lord, as if we were to <hi>Dy</hi> when we come. And at this <hi>Holy Table,</hi> where <hi>Man Eats Angels Food,</hi> Let us <hi>Fix</hi> our <hi>Meditations</hi> on our LORD JESUS CHRIST, with all possible <hi>Attention,</hi> with all suitable <hi>Affection.</hi> Thus, <hi>Behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, as in a Glass, the Glory of the Lord, we shall be Changed into the same Image, from Glory to Glory, as by the Spirit of the Lord.</hi> Now, 'tis that <hi>Glory</hi> that makes an <hi>Angel!</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>V.</hi> An <hi>Heart</hi> much Affected with the Lord JESUS CHRIST, will procure the <hi>Face of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel,</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:185005:13"/> unto the <hi>man,</hi> who hath an <hi>Heart</hi> so affected. Unto the <hi>Angels,</hi> there is nothing so precious, &amp; nothing so glorious, as the Lord JESUS CHRIST; yea, 'tis our CHRIST, that makes the best part of their <hi>Heaven</hi> for them. Our Lord JESUS CHRIST, is, as the Apostle Enumerates it among the <hi>Mysteries</hi> and <hi>Evidences</hi> of our Faith, in 1 Tim. 3. 16. <hi>Seen of Angels.</hi> But how <hi>Seen?</hi> Truly, <hi>Seen</hi> with Wonders, and <hi>Seen</hi> with Raptures, and <hi>Seen</hi> with Endless <hi>Hallelujahs.</hi> Would we be Like the <hi>Angels?</hi> Then Let our Lord JESUS CHRIST be <hi>Seen</hi> by us, as the <hi>Best Thing</hi> in Heaven and Earth, and as infinitely <hi>Better</hi> than the very <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> themselves. At the <hi>Incarnation</hi> of our Lord JESUS CHRIST. What were the Songs of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels?</hi> in Luk. 2. 14. <hi>There was a multitude of the Heavenly Host, praising of God, and saying, Glory to God in the Highest!</hi> Would we be like the <hi>Angels?</hi> Let us then join in a Consort with those <hi>Morning Stars,</hi> and <hi>Sons of God.</hi> It was with <hi>Joy Unspeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able and full of Glory,</hi> that the <hi>Angels</hi> attended up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Lord JESUS CHRIST, first throughout His <hi>Humiliation,</hi> and then, unto His <hi>Exaltation</hi> Let the whole of <hi>That,</hi> be the most Ravishing Subject of our <hi>Contemplation;</hi> Let us Love to see our Lord JESUS CHRIST, first <hi>Suffering,</hi> and then <hi>Entring into His Glory.</hi> And let our Acclamations, be like those of the <hi>Angels,</hi> upon those marvellous Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pensations of the Grace of God! When the <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gels</hi> do <hi>Look</hi> on the Lord JESUS CHRIST, they are <hi>Covered</hi> with Astonishment, and cry out, O
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:185005:14"/>
               <hi>Holy, Holy, Holy Lord of Hosts, all Heaven is full of thy Glory!</hi> And shall not <hi>we</hi> so Look on that our <hi>Lord of Glory?</hi> When the <hi>Angels</hi> do <hi>Speak</hi> of our Lord JESUS CHRIST, they make a most Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent mention of His <hi>Holy and Reverend Name,</hi> and say, <hi>Oh! there is none among the Sons of the Mighty, that may be compared unto this Lord.</hi> And shall not <hi>we</hi> so speak of that Great <hi>King,</hi> with a <hi>Tongue, like the Pen of a Ready Writer?</hi> Something of <hi>Christ,</hi> the <hi>Angels</hi> must have; they would think them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to be <hi>Starved,</hi> if they had not this <hi>Manna</hi> to Feed upon! Syrs, Let the <hi>Meat</hi> of our Souls be the <hi>Fruit</hi> growing on this <hi>Tree of Life;</hi> &amp; Let the <hi>Drink</hi> of our Souls be, the <hi>Honey of this Rock:</hi> This is the daily Repast of <hi>Angels;</hi> This Nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rishment will <hi>Angelify</hi> us in a little while. What shall I say? The <hi>Mystery of CHRIST,</hi> is the most grateful Contemplation of the <hi>Angels:</hi> Those <hi>Cherubims</hi> about the <hi>Ark of God,</hi> we are told, in 1 Pet. 1 12. <hi>They Desire to Look into these Things.</hi> I say then, <hi>Go and do Likewise.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>VI.</hi> If we would always Behave our selves as before the <hi>Face of Angels,</hi> we should at length ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the <hi>Face of an Angel,</hi> by the Exactness, the Circumspection, the Accuracy of our Behaviour. It was a Good <hi>Memento,</hi> written upon a Study-Wall, <hi>Angeli adstant;</hi> or, <hi>The Angels of God stand by!</hi> Did men Remember the Eye of the Invisible <hi>Angels</hi> upon them, in all their ways, how grave, how cautious, how pious would they be; and at Last, how like unto those <hi>Angels!</hi> If a man, were
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:185005:14"/> as bad as <hi>Balaam</hi> himself, yet the bare suspicion of having the Eye of some <hi>Angel</hi> upon him, would be enough to stop him from Rushing on to <hi>Sin. Why shouldest thou Sin,</hi> says the Wise man, in Eccl. 5. 6. <hi>Before the Angel?</hi> If we were <hi>Wise,</hi> we should often think, <hi>I am now before some Angel!</hi> and that Thought would make us <hi>Wise.</hi> The Aged Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle said unto a younger Minister, <hi>I charge thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Elect Angels:</hi> from whence 'tis infallibly sure, That the <hi>Elect Angels</hi> take notice, how we Acquit our selves, each one in his <hi>Charge.</hi> Said the Psalmist, in Psal. 138. 1. <hi>Before the Gods I will Sing praise unto thee:</hi> The LXX translate it, <hi>I will sing praise unto thee, before the Angels.</hi> Christi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, The <hi>Angels</hi> take Notice of us, in all our <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployments,</hi> yea, in our Closest <hi>Retirements.</hi> We give no <hi>Praises</hi> to God, we Perform no <hi>Duties,</hi> we En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure no <hi>Troubles,</hi> we Resist no <hi>Temptations,</hi> but the <hi>Angels</hi> of God, are the <hi>Witnesses</hi> of what we do; we are a <hi>Spectacle to Angels</hi> in all of our <hi>Encounters.</hi> Well, Now Let our <hi>Deportment,</hi> be mightily under the Influence of this Consideration; <hi>The Angels take Notice; What Report will the Angels of God, give of my Behaviours!</hi> It has been propounded as a <hi>Rule of Prudence,</hi> for a man, wherever he comes, to Imagine, that there is present some Eminent, Wise, and Good man, to see and hear all that passes. <hi>Man,</hi> There is an <hi>Angel</hi> to see and hear all that passes, wherever thou comest; This is no <hi>meer Imagination.</hi> Could we, like the Servant of the Prophet, in the Mount, see the unseen Regi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:185005:15"/> of the World, by the Subordinate Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Angels,</hi> what an <hi>Awe,</hi> what an <hi>Awe,</hi> what an <hi>Awe</hi> would it strike us with! The <hi>Angels</hi> of the Lord see, how men are Disposed, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployed, for the Service of Their Lord, and gladly contribute their unknown Assistences unto that Service. But it cannot be any other than a Grief unto those <hi>Angels,</hi> to see <hi>Enormities,</hi> in those, for whose welfare they are concerned. If they have <hi>Joy</hi> over a <hi>Paenitent,</hi> they must needs have some sort of <hi>Grief</hi> over a <hi>Transgressor.</hi> Yea, in all pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bability, the miscarriages of such offenders, work in them a sort of <hi>Distast,</hi> which inclines them, on many accounts, to withdraw from the Offenders, until they have <hi>Washed</hi> themselves over again, <hi>In the Fountain set open for Sin &amp; for Uncleanness.</hi> Now, Let this consideration accompany us, in all our Walk; and let the <hi>Eye</hi> of an <hi>Angel</hi> be more to us, than the <hi>Eye</hi> of a <hi>Cato,</hi> could be to any <hi>Roman.</hi> The <hi>Face of Angels</hi> will at last be gain'd, by such a Consideration!</p>
            <p n="7">
               <hi>VII.</hi> Let us Beware of every <hi>Sin;</hi> for <hi>Sin</hi> will Turn a <hi>Man</hi> into a <hi>Devil.</hi> Oh! Vile SIN, horrid SIN, cursed SIN; or, to speak a more Pungent word, than all of That; Oh, SINFUL Sin; how Pernicious art thou unto the Souls of Men! Tis said, in 1 Joh. 3. 8. <hi>He that Committeth Sin, is of the Devil. Holiness</hi> will make men <hi>Incarnate Angels;</hi> but <hi>Wickedness</hi> will make them <hi>Devils Incarnate.</hi> An Impenitent <hi>Sinner;</hi> hath he the <hi>Face of an An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel?</hi> No, but the <hi>Heart of a Devil</hi> in him. Let
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:185005:15"/> your <hi>Zeal</hi> against all <hi>Sin</hi> then, be like that of the <hi>Seraphim.</hi> The <hi>Angels,</hi> are <hi>Seraphims,</hi> or Burning ones; They <hi>Burn</hi> [and so let <hi>us!]</hi> against all <hi>Sin,</hi> because of its being so contrary &amp; provoking to their most <hi>Holy Lord.</hi> Sirs, Mark it; If any of you wittingly, and willingly, Sin against God, you do as the <hi>Devils</hi> do, and as the <hi>Devils</hi> would have you to do, and as our Lord Jesus Christ speaks, in Joh. 8. 44. <hi>Ye are of your Father the Devil, and the Lusts of your Father ye will do.</hi> Dreadful words! There is the <hi>Image</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> and there is the <hi>Practice</hi> of the <hi>Devil,</hi> in every SIN. To <hi>Commit</hi> SIN, is <hi>Humane;</hi> to <hi>Indulge</hi> it, will be <hi>Diabolical.</hi> But especially, there is much of the <hi>Devil</hi> in <hi>Aposta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sy</hi> from Good Beginnings. Of the <hi>Devils,</hi> we find in Jude 6. <hi>They kept not their First Estate:</hi> They once joined, it seems, in Praising of God, with the <hi>Angels</hi> of the Blessed Regions; but they <hi>Left</hi> it all. You that have <hi>Left</hi> the <hi>Societies,</hi> and the <hi>Exercises,</hi> of Christianity, wherein you were <hi>at First</hi> Engaged; Behold, who your <hi>Leader</hi> is! The first and great <hi>Apostate,</hi> the <hi>Devil,</hi> is your <hi>Leader,</hi> in this <hi>Desertion;</hi> And, alas, whither will he <hi>Lead</hi> you? There is much of the <hi>Devil</hi> also, in <hi>Hypocrisy</hi> under Good Professions. When there was a Secret, Rotten <hi>Hypocrite,</hi> among the Disciples of our Lord. Our Lord said, in Joh. 6. 70. <hi>He is a Devil:</hi> Indeed, the <hi>Devil</hi> is never so much a <hi>Devil,</hi> as when <hi>Transformed</hi> into <hi>an Angel of Light.</hi> When strict pretenders, and pleaders, and it may be, Preachers of the <hi>Gospel,</hi> shall yet <hi>Cloak some</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:185005:16"/>
               <hi>Hidden Practices of Dishonesty</hi> under their fair pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences, Behold, Men playing the <hi>Devil</hi> horribly. What shall I say more? The <hi>Devil</hi> is an <hi>Unclean</hi> Spirit, a <hi>Lying</hi> Spirit, a <hi>Proud</hi> Spirit, a Spirit full of <hi>Envy.</hi> Oh! Take heed lest you be of such a <hi>Spirit,</hi> and so, Lest you Perish <hi>with the Devil and his Angels,</hi> throughout Eternal Ages.</p>
            <p>Thus, the <hi>Rules</hi> of becoming <hi>Angelical,</hi> have been set before us.</p>
            <p>But if we do now Humbly Reflect upon our selves, for our not Living up to these <hi>Rules;</hi> we cannot easily be more Humble in such Reflections, than was that MAN OF GOD, the Reverend, JOSHUA MOODEY, who from his <hi>Essayes</hi> to obtain the <hi>Face of Angels,</hi> is now gone unto the <hi>Place of Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All the Churches of <hi>NEW ENGLAND,</hi> Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered him, as a Person, whom an Eminency both in <hi>Sense,</hi> and in <hi>Grace,</hi> had made Considerable. All the Churches of BOSTON, Enjoy'd and Admired, his Accomplishments for the <hi>Evangelical Ministry,</hi> many years together. The Church of <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> (a part of the Country that very much ow'd its <hi>Life</hi> unto him!) Cryes out, of, <hi>A Dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Wound,</hi> in his <hi>Death;</hi> and is ready to cry out, <hi>Our Breach is Great like the Sea; who can heal it?</hi> His <hi>Labours</hi> in the Gospel, were frequent and fervent; whereof the <hi>Press</hi> hath given some <hi>Last<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,</hi> as the <hi>Pulpit</hi> gave many <hi>Lively</hi> Testimonies: and unto his Cares to Edify his Flock by <hi>Sermons,</hi> he added more than Ordinary Cares to do it by
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:185005:16"/>
               <hi>Visits:</hi> No man Perhaps being a kinder <hi>Visitant.</hi> He was not only Ready to <hi>Do Good,</hi> but also to <hi>Suffer</hi> for doing it; and as he was Exemplarily Zealous for a <hi>Scriptural Purity</hi> in the Worship of the Lord Jesus Christ, so, he cheerfully Submitted unto an <hi>Imprisonment,</hi> for that <hi>Cause of God, and of this Country;</hi> wherein, like <hi>Stephen,</hi> he had the Honour to be the <hi>First,</hi> that Suffered in that way for that <hi>Cause,</hi> in these parts of the World. Briefly, For <hi>Piety,</hi> for <hi>Charity,</hi> and for <hi>Faithfulness</hi> to the main Interests of our Churches; all that knew him, and know the worth of these things, wish that among the <hi>Survivers,</hi> he may have many <hi>Followers.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He was of a very Robust and Hardy Constitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and a notable Exception to the General Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mark, <hi>Raro solent Ingenia insigniter faelicia, Robusta sortiri Corpora;</hi> and, it may be, too <hi>Prodigal</hi> of his <hi>Athletick Strength,</hi> in doing the Service, whereto a Good Master called him. Nevertheless, when a <hi>Complication</hi> of Distempers, was diverse Months before his Dissolution, brought thereby upon him, he Exceedingly Lamented, <hi>His Neglect,</hi> (as he ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted it) <hi>of his past Opportunities to be Serviceable.</hi> At Length, Coming to <hi>Boston,</hi> for Advice about the Recovery of his Lost Health, his Distempers here so grew upon him, as to Threaten a Quick <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eriod unto his Pilgrimage. His Distressed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hurch at <hi>Portsmouth</hi> now Importunately made their <hi>Prayer</hi> with <hi>Fasting</hi> before the <hi>Great Shepherd of the Sheep,</hi> that they might not be deprived of
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:185005:17"/> so Rich a Blessing; and he was himself Excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly desirous to have Returned unto <hi>Portsmouth,</hi> that he might establish his Flock yet further a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst all Temptations to forsake <hi>the Right wayes of the Lord.</hi> But Heaven determines otherwise.</p>
            <p>When the Last Summons of <hi>Death</hi> came to be Served upon him, he had neither <hi>Time,</hi> nor <hi>Strength,</hi> to speak very much; and they that have spoken much while they <hi>Live,</hi> sometimes must not speak very much at their <hi>Death.</hi> His Discourses, were generally full of <hi>Self-Condemna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> and indeed, that man knows not how to <hi>Dy,</hi> who thinks to Dy otherwise, than <hi>Condemning of himself,</hi> Exceedingly. The most of what he said, was, I suppose, unto a Minister, who Visited him, the Day before his Expiration. Unto that Minister, he Signifyed, That he <hi>was Rejoycing in the Hope of the Glory of God;</hi> That he <hi>was Longing to Go to the Precious Christ, whom he had Chose and Serv'd;</hi> That <hi>the Spirit of Christ, had Comfortably taken away from him the Fear of DEATH.</hi> When that Minister urged him, to Leave with him, any special Desire, that he should Judge pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per to be mentioned, He said, <hi>The Life of the Churches! The Life of the Churches! and the Dying Power of Godliness in them; I beseech you to Look af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that!</hi> The Minister at last said, <hi>The Lord Jes<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Christ, is now, Sir, going to do for you, as once</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> Joshua <hi>[your Names-sake!] He is just going to take from you, your old, sorry, ragged Garments. Those of</hi>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:185005:17"/>
               <hi>your Flesh, and clothe you with change of Raiment, with the Garments of Heavenly Glory, and give you a place among His Angels:</hi> Whereto he Replied, with some Transport, <hi>I Believe it! I Believe it!</hi> After this, he said little, but Lay in an uneasy Drowsiness, until the Afternoon of the Day following; which was, <hi>The Lords Day;</hi> and then, even on the Day, whereon he had so often been <hi>in the Spirit,</hi> he went unto the Blessed <hi>World of Spirits;</hi> on the Day, which he had so often Sanctifyed in a <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Rest,</hi> he went into his <hi>Eternal Rest.</hi> A <hi>Fatal Day</hi> was this Day unto our Land! It is an Omen of a sad Fate unto a Land, when the <hi>Angels</hi> do say, <hi>Migremus hinc;</hi> Let us be gone! How far he had the <hi>Face of an Angel,</hi> while he Sojourned here, no doubt <hi>Envy</hi> may <hi>Cavil;</hi> and I have sometimes, with wonder seen it, in the poor <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergumens</hi> among us, that when the <hi>Minister,</hi> who might be the most likely to do them Good, came unto them, the Fiends that possessed them, would make the Ministers <hi>Face</hi> Look so Dirty and Swarthy, that they must by no means acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him. This I may venture to say, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Flattery: It is Long ago, that in another <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>se than <hi>Aquinas,</hi> we call'd him, <hi>An Angeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Doctor;</hi> And he has now attained, <hi>The Face of an Angel,</hi> without the least <hi>Wrinkle</hi> in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> He is, with <hi>Stephen,</hi> and the <hi>Angels of God,</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>ne to Behold the Glory of the Lord JESUS <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>HRIST, and bear a part with the <hi>Many An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> round about the Throne, saying, Worthy is the</hi>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:185005:18"/>
               <hi>Lamb that was Slain!</hi> I cannot but Recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend him to you, as one that was, <hi>A Candi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date of the Angelical Life;</hi> and sollicit you to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, not only the <hi>Lessons,</hi> and <hi>Counsils,</hi> and <hi>Warnings,</hi> which you have had from him, in private or publick Dispensations, but also his <hi>Example,</hi> to <hi>Follow</hi> him, wherein he <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed,</hi> [and in many things he Followed!] <hi>the Lord JESUS CHRIST.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:185005:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>